<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Dilawar's Blog</title>
		<description>Craving for existence.</description>
		<link>http://dilawar.github.io</link>
		
			<item>
				<title>Caste and other 'branded for life' thingy</title>
				<description>Social life in India is marked by subordination of individual to the group. This
is not to say that Indian society knows 'anything of individuals' but the claims
of group often prevail of claim of an individual [1]. Family, being a universal
social group, is a good candidate for comparison and contrast. An Indian family
makes its claims most vigorously at the time when education and marriage of
children are being arranged. Such claims legitimize themselves by a value-system
based on customs. Customs justify themselves by asserting their antiquity over
anything else. If a group makes its claim on individual and expect from him a
moral obligation to be loyal to it, then in return it offers patronage and a
sense of security. Majority of Indians who feel safe and secure only in some
'group' or extended kinship develop a deep urge to be identified with a group :
Jats, Brahmins, Tamils, Gujrati, IITians, IIMians etc. I do not wish to comment
on identities based on language or religion for they are universal but I wish to
point out those groups which are unique to South Asia namely Caste and its
modern avatars.



It has been pointed out that intelligentsia tends to neglect social customs and
'habits of heart' which students of societies are obsessed with. We find these
'habit of hearts' and social customs most important and defining feature of a
society. I was struck by more by similarities than differences between rural and
urban India. Coming from a rural Western Uttar Pradesh where people are
segregated according to their castes in villages, it was surprising to see that
people are segregated according to 'class' ; in cities government has its own
HIG, MIG and LIG residential areas where people are segregated according to
their class. In villages, a high value is placed over areas where high-caste
people in live. In my first encounter with city people, my classmates put
similar values on 'posh-areas'. They can be seen enquiring about such areas
whenever they visit another city. It would not be a great exaggeration to
suggest that educated and uneducated Indians do not differ from each other in
very fundamental way. Nonetheless, educated Indians tends to be self-consciously
virtuous to an unusual degree. They are much more successful at hiding those
customs and habits which they have come to regard as backward, feudal or
embarrassing.



Caste is an institute which still governs life of Indians, educated and
uneducated alike. This is not to say that changes have not occurred in Indian
society. Indians, who live in villages and towns, are realistic and vocal about
castes. They don't feel any embarrassment talking about about it. But 'educated'
Indians in cities and towns suffer from a certain kind of myopia about their own
society. They are very sensitive to the question of caste. Any conversation on
caste with them will reveal a some amount of embarrassment and a great deal of
ignorance. Any debate on caste, unlike most of the debates in India, generates
less heat but it lends itself very easily to polemic.



Most Indians, among whom I roam, consider caste an unmixed evil and wish it out
of existence. I am not suggesting that it is a good thing. Most of them like to
think that caste does not exists in their society or at least their personal
affairs are not governed by it. When prodded somewhat, they would concede that
it still exists in many if not most part of India but they themselves have
nothing to do with it. These days they are more explicit about these feelings
and many of them subscribe to two-nation theory : everything embarrassing and
backward belong to Bharat; anything modern and forward looking belongs to India
of whose they are the torch-bearer. When pointed out that inter-caste marriages
in their own 'Indian societies' are still very rare (though increasing), they
can not explain it in a straight-forward way. Also their friend circle rarely
have people from different categories. It is all too natural for a human being
to sweep under the carpet those customs which embarrasses him and not speak of
it. Moreover if tormented long enough about caste, they might even accuse one of
having a morbid or obscurantist temperament, if not a medieval mentality.



No student of Indian society can avoid the question of caste. It was and still
is of fundamental value which governs Indian society. Caste provides many clues
which enables us to understand Indian society in better ways. It is not just an
organization which ranks people high and low, it is also a system of values
which gives a ideological justification for prevent hierarchies. Indian
intellectuals have had a mixed record in predicting the role of caste and
analyzing its nature . Marxists denied caste its place in Indian society and
they denied it categorically that caste plays any important role in Indian
society. For them class was of utmost importance and caste was mere a byproduct
of class-struggle. On the other hand, many free-wheeling intellectuals these
days like to assert that Indian preoccupation with caste has seen little or no
change [2].


*****


It is not the existence of caste but its longevity which has surprised many
social anthropologists. Caste is perhaps the most ingenious social invention
ever devised by man to keep social hierarchy in place. For this reason (and
novelty attached to it), it has been studied by anthropologists world over and a
large body of comparative literature has been produced. Various definitions and
theories about its origin and evolution have been proposed and debated. If one
can find his way out of this vast literature on caste, it can improve our
understanding of our society. Max Weber thought that it was the 'concern for
status' which was at the center of the obsession with the caste. For him, caste
was a status group. [Late Prof. Louis
Dumont](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Dumont), who was the leading European
authority on kinship, found root of caste in religion ('Holism' as he called it)
and he criticized Weber for attaching caste with status too much. Also, a racial
theory has been proposed that caste was a product of two groups - immigrants and
natives - coming in close encounter with each other. The immigrants Aryans tried
to protect the purity of their blood by intermarriage (notice the voluntarism) ,
therefore endogamous closed groups. These groups were called castes. This theory
has a great appeal to modern mentality but it does not explain the longevity of
caste.



What is important to us here is not the definitions and their comparisons but
how caste is perceived by common folks. It has been said that caste initially
meant 'division of labour' and I can not say how many Indians like to see it
that way. In many of theories proposed by apologetic Indians about the nature of
caste, acceptance of it is believed to be voluntary : that people accepted their
inferior status by choice and it was not forced by laws or ideologies, religious
or secular. It sounds strange to me, though not wholly unconvincing, that that
indeed was the case. For I do not know any large civilization like ours in which
a large section of people accepted a 'inferior brand' by choice without showing
any sign of discomfort.



Another view of caste (rather a definition of it) was proposed by Ms. [Irawati
Karve](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irawati_Karve). Mrs. Karve classified Indian
society as made up of 'real groups'. These groups which entered the system at a
given time was recognizable by its customs and the physical characteristics of
its members. Perhaps this is not how our ancestors saw castes but this is closer
to how we see them. Our ancestors build a theory based on purity and pollution
to justify the caste based on hierarchy. Brahmins were the proponent of this
theory and they thought of themselves the purest one. They took great care not
to pollute themselves by coming in the touch with polluting castes. Not only
certain groups were polluting, there were works which were considered ritually
defiling and to engage in those works were to loose one's caste which was
equivalent to civil death. Much of the Indian contempt toward manual work has
its root in it.



There were elaborated rules on exchange of 'roti and beti' (food and daughter).
One can take daughter of a lower-caste family in marriage but can not give one
to them; and one can give food to the lower castes but could not accept it from
them. These practices were very elaborate and widespread in the past. Practice
of unaccountability is not as severe these days even in villages where it has
been replaced by atrocities against dalits to some extent. However, practices
related to marriage have not changed much, especially when one arranges marriage
of his daughters. In matters related to marriages, the obsession with purity ran
really deep. The upper middle class section of society which saw themselves as
socially-forward those days used to marry their daughters before the onset of
puberty (in a state of being pure) and those who delayed the marriage of their
daughters beyond puberty invited a great deal of castigation and reprimand.
Those who consider themselves socially-forward these days do just the opposite.
Interestingly, the age of marriage of girls was one of criteria which Mandal
commission used to describe social backwardness. How can one say nothing has
changed in this country when something which was morally-backward to our
grandmothers and mothers has become a symbol of social forwardness to our
sisters and daughters?


******


My intention in this post to find similarities between castes and certain groups
or rather 'brands' (as they are often called) with which some people in this
country voluntarily attach to themselves. And I wish to put one of such brands
called [IITian](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Institutes_of_Technology)
under sociological enquiry. Other similar brands are students of IIM, Indian
Administrative Service, and officers in armed forces. I'll restrict myself to
IITian for I have been living among them for many years now.



When I joined IIT Bombay in 2007 for post-graduation studies, at the time of
orientation enough hints were given by Head of the Department those days that he
considers UGs superior to PGs. These beliefs may not be acknowledged by all
professors but those who took their undergraduate degrees from IITs are most
likely to have one. For when they proudly claim to be IITians, they are not
claiming to be a heir of some intellectual tradition. They simply don't have
one. They want to assert something which is widely acknowledged : the
superiority attach to this symbol called IITian. If there is no superiority
attached to a symbol, a upwardly socially mobile Indian would not be fascinated
by it. It was amusing to be introduced to hierarchy on the campus on the very
first day by HOD (He took his B.Tech. from this IIT) which was known to us
anyway. Those days I saw IITias more of a faction than a 'brand'. It is a form
of pseudo-kinship which Indian usually make wherever they go. The reason is
perhaps more psychological than social. An Indian finds very hard to be himself
and he loves to be surrounded by 'his' people : a sort of pseudo family. He feel
safe and secure only among his kinsmen. They have a kinship based on the name of
the institutes for given their size they could no longer find enough people
belonging to any other shared identity. As the size of IIT Bombay is increasing,
so is the numbers of other 'real groups' : Bengali, Marathi, Malayalam and other
such groups are easily noticeable and are actively promoting themselves though
they have not yet taken the center stage as they do in many other universities.
The shared identity called IITian trumps them all.



It was a logo on their t-shirt which caught my attention. if I remember
correctly it claimed that they are 'branded for life'. More I thought about it,
more I became obsessed with the idea that it may be some form of a caste. For
caste also brands an individual for life. The brand called 'IITian' is different
from brand like 'engineer'. This is a subscription-based brand for one has to do
some engineering to keep his subscription active. On the other hand, the brand
IITian like a caste, does not depend on subscription. Even if they don't do any
engineering or technological work, they can still wear it proudly. Like Brahmins
who do not study classical text or Chamars who do not do any leather-work
anymore are still seen as Brahmins and Chamars.



Who belongs to this caste/brand? The undergraduate students of Indian Institute
of Technology definitely do. And many postgraduates would love to have it, at
least outside the campus where the value of such a tag is widely acknowledged.
This process where a inferior caste mimics the social customs of superior caste
to gain a high social status was called 'Sanskritization' by M. N. Srinivas [
Sankritization, Srinivas in 'Social change in modern India'] . Various castes
indeed changed their status from ST to OBC to other general categories. Many of
them have successfully reverted back after quotas in jobs and educational
institute were offered. Fully Sanskritized castes were in the processes of what
is called by Srninivas 'Westernization'. Both Sankritization and Westerisation
are complex phenomenon and can be observed almost every section of Indian
society. In our case, the UG are in the process of Westernisation (already
Sanskraitzed) by chasing respective social symbols : foreign degrees and
internships. The post-graduates are also actively engaged in the process of
Westernisation but they are in the process of Sanskritization too; by mimicking
the customs of U.G. When I joined in 2007, there was no social-custom of
'profile reading' among post-graduates (the tone and language used by them is
comparatively extremely civilized). It has now become commonplace among them
too. Therefore, it is safe to say that not only superiority of UG is asserted,
it is also widely acknowledged if only implicitly.



Unlike castes, access to this brand is fixed not by birth but to success in a
competitive examination called Joint Entrance Examination (JEE). Much they like
to separate birth with merit, it is a known fact, to the discomfort to
egalitarian world over, that merit if not intelligence and birth are closely
related. Access to post-graduation in IITs is fixed by another competitive
examination called Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE). These
examinations tests abilities of menial mental manipulation but they are valued
highly especially by those who fails in them. There is some confusion if
post-graduate students can also claim this brand. My experience tells me that
the undergraduates in IITs are at best half-hearted about sharing their 'brand'
with post-graduates. The reason for it : a trait of caste named exclusivity. One
professor in my department revealed something deeply psychological : the dual
degree do not write M. Tech. on their resume, they write senior undergraduate
(or something like that if my memory serves me wrong).



The 'JEE crackers', as they like to call themselves, consider themselves
superior to 'GATE crackers' because of the fact that almost all those who writes
GATE must have written JEE in their school days. This is largely true for cities
and towns. Anyone who thinks of himself 'smart enough' and have access to at
least a middle class family writes this examination. So if they were really as
'intelligent' or 'smart', this theory suggests, they could have been successful
in JEE in the first place. Therefore they are inferior. This belief is so
widespread that it is never questioned for one can ask if 'intelligence' is an
innate quality and does not depend of mental exercises done daily than why so
many of 'JEE crackers' can only go through in more than one attempts. What one
can make out of the intelligence of those who failed in first attempt and got a
really impressive score in the second or third attempt? I wonder if they ever
told themselves that they are as intelligence now as they were before cracking
any examination. Besides the claim of having a superior intellect is at best
phony for it is coming from a group which is yet to produce their equivalent of
Bose, Raman and Saha.



This modern Indian obsession with merit can be compared with the ancient Hindu
obsession with purity. Both purity and intelligence are hard to define but none
of it diminish their respective obsession. The Brahmins may not have produced a
definite commentary on what purity really is -- consistency and universality
were never issues on which they lost any sleep -- but they elaborated in great
details many customs and practises by which purity can be violated. The modern
times have similar attitude toward merit (which is confused with intellect).
Like purity in our medieval or ancient order, merit is of supreme value to all
competitive industrial society and it is natural that they love to measure it.
There is still some doubt about the nature of merit and intelligence but as one
American social scientist has put it, 'Intelligence, like electricity, is easy
to measure than to define'. So these societies with America leading the way go
on measuring intelligence with vengeance.




******


'Branded for life' is minimum any caste promises. Granted that one's place in
IITs is not fixed by birth as it is with the caste. But the idea here is not to
find a logical equivalent but to highlight many similarities. Being born in a
particular type of family makes it easier to get access to these brands. One
still needs to do some work and requires some luck but what about those whose
life chances are severely restricted because they were born in the wrong type of
family by the accident of birth? Just for the sake of argument, I would like to
classify caste IITian as a twice-born or 'dwijha' castes. You are born in a
middle class family which has enough material and intellectual capital. Such
families want to secure the best possible education for their offspring. The
first birth is this caste is when one is an 'inspiring IITian' and there are so
many of them. The second birth in this caste happens when one cracks JEE after a
year or two (or perhaps more) training in a coaching center : a sort of a
'yagopaveet sanskar'. In middle class families, children are not only groomed
from a very early age to join such elite-clubs they are also taught to value the
status attached with it. And they must feel really fascinated by these brands
which in due time become a part of their identity. Weather or not they do
justice to the name of the institute they are so fascinated with, they take
these identities to their graveyard with them. Any attack on this identity are
not taken lightly.



It is then natural that they feel a need to preserve the value of their brand
(purity of their caste). The reactions toward opening up more IITs among IITians
consolidated my belief. They were concerned that opening up new IITs in
otherwise mediocre educational system would devalue the brand IIT. It does not
follow that IIT Gandhinagar will devalue IIT Bombay. And they were not concerned
with IIT Bombay as such anyway. There concern is with the 'brand/caste' IITian.
They are perhaps interested in the well-being of their institute and its
reputation but they are also very interested in preserving their brand. There
must not be a large numbers of IITians (even if all of them are undergraduates)
else the exclusivity (purity of caste) will be compromised. Many of them do not
like sharing it with post-graduates and suggests that IIT should be UG only.
What sort of professor would like to teach in a college where he would spend his
time only with UGs and with no research students, whether of not they have
'sharp antennas'?



The obsession with hierarchy is fundamental to caste. The hierarchy does not
lead itself automatically to authority. My right hand is superior to my left
hand without having any authority over it. The outcome of hierarchy is the
feeling of superiority and inferiority. It is not to say that these feelings are
bad one. If there are no such feelings, no profession and individual will grow.
But these feelings in our society are usually group based. No institute can
function if it does not discriminate among individuals as superior or inferior
for a certain kind of job. I find it irritating, to put is mildly, when I see
obsession with groups based discrimination.



On Indian universities, departments are ranked superior or inferior according to
a well established model of hierarchy. EE and CSE are superior to other
departments for reason too obvious to all of us. It is a feature of a society
which 'hierarchicise' everything : people and places, gods, festivals are
heirachicised but also intellectual disciplines according to some of the most
pettiest reasons. One can classify students on IIT Bombay campuses when one is
inclined to classify according to a caste as following : B. Tech and D. D. are
General Castes, M. Tech. are Other Backward Caste (OBC), and Ph.D. are
Untouchables. And to stay here to pursue another degree is equivalent of loosing
one's caste for an inferior one. Who has heard of many Indian loosing their
caste (even metaphorically) to some inferior one in a right state of mind?



The hierarchy of department is well established according to ranks of students
joins them and remains fairly constant for every year a fixed section of merit
lists which goes to certain department. The counseling for admission is farce
and it is there because a modern university must have one. No student is really
interested at the time of joining in knowing what he wants to do in his life for
he is not raised this way : he is greatly stimulated and rarely inspired. And
once he got the symbols he was fascinated with, his stimulation wears off. 
There is simply no pressure on him to excel anymore when his kinsmen do not put
a premium on it. Parents impose their will on their children without any sense
of guilt or concern for their status depends on the status of their children.
This is natural in a society where individual do not have it place under the
sun. Getting into jobs which does not do justice with their current status
causes them a great agony. The status is not only attached to jobs but also to
internships at certain places and to extra-curricular activities of certain
type.



Among the highest Varna (The UGs), there are sub-castes. When there is [no PG to
compare their penises
with](http://dilawarrajput.wordpress.com/2012/12/16/an-open-letter-to-iit-undergraduate/),
they turn to these sub-castes for comparison. They compare according to JEE Rank
which correlate well with their department. Not only there are sub-castes
according to departments, another 'varna' has come into being. This one is based
on the type of JEE one has cracked. Old time IITians love to compare themselves
on the nature of JEE. Their's was superior to what these days IITians are
cracking (A, B, C, D kind). They take pride in telling them and others that they
have gone through much rigorous subjective examination than objective-questions
based examination these days. Much has been said about the nature of questions.
It is a pity that too little has been said if the new JEE or GATE has lost their
discriminatory powers. It is very important for an institute to make sure that
its examinations discriminate effectively among its residents : students (not
only those who are inspiring to join but also those who have joined them) and
staff alike. Some concerns was raised about the nature of questions asked in
examinations is valid for no one can deny the falling level of sophistication of
problems. The root-cause for continuing with objective-examination lies
somewhere else. It is not entirely due to easy management of objective
examination which has promoted A,B,C,D kind of examination. Objective
examinations are, above everything else, least prone to invite the accusation of
unfair evaluations. And it is very important in a society where anyone can
accuse anyone out of habit.



The longevity of caste teaches us two things : the obsession with value system
which justify hierarchy and promotes the concern for status as value. Where
there is a hierarchy which is rarely questioned and widely recognized as a
natural scheme of thing, one will find a great deal of similarity in it with
classical caste system. Caste system in the past legitimize its hierarchy by the
idea of pollution and purity. The 'branded for life thingy' discussed here as
caste legitimize its hierarchy by the theory of merit and intelligence.

The early description of castes assumes its root in rituals and both Indians and
Western student agreed on it. This belief is now on a shaky ground. For who can
deny the irreversible decline in the ritualistic aspect of caste? But this
decline did not result in similar decline in caste system. It is important to
think of secular aspects of caste system which has not declined with time.

    
NOTE : Old version of this article &lt;a
href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!folder/samwad/samwadiitb/qrlC1_0ckIg&quot;&gt;was
posted here&lt;/a&gt;. First 3 comments on this article was on this version. I am
deleting these comments for their historical value.
    
</description>
				<published>2013-02-20 01:32:09 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/IIT Bombay/Indian Society/Caste/2013/02/20/Caste-and-other-branded-for-life-thingy/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Neglect of history and obsession with the past </title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of our historians noted the lack of taste for accurate historical writing
rather ruefully. 'India, for its great literary heritage', noted D. D.  Kosambi,
'has produced no historical writers comparable to Herodotus,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thucydides&quot;&gt;Thucydides&lt;/a&gt;, Polybius, Livy, Tacitus'.
This is despite of the fact that many Indian kings of the middle ages were  not
only 'incomparably superior in their education and literally ability to
contemporary rulers in Europe', they also 'personally led great armies to
victory in heavy warfare'. None of them considered it worthwhile to write
anything comparable to Caesar's Commentaries or Xenophon's Anabasis. 'The
tradition was of graceful court drama, an occasional hymn in praise of the gods,
or a witty epigram'.  Kosambi commented further that only Rajatarangani by a
Kasmirian named &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalhana&quot;&gt;Kalhana&lt;/a&gt;  (A.D.  1149-50)
and continued by two successors can be called anything like a historical
document. Unfortunately, 'this chronicles suffer from all the mannered
conventions of Sanskrit poetry, in particular the fatal double entendre that
manages only to obscure whatever reality the author meant to portray'. Even when
the period Kalhana was describing was 'a period was of desperate struggle
between the central power and feudal lords in Kashmir', he cared not to note the
'actual time and place' which can 'hardly be compared in quality, depth, content
to the account by Thucydides of the Peloponnesian war'. For the rest of the
country, till the Muslim period, we have nothing even as good as Kalhana. Some
older written records which survived such as Puranas ( = the ancient stories),
'are only religious fables and cant with whatever historical content the works
once possessed heavily encrusted by myth, diluted with semi-religious legends,
effaced during successive redactions copied by innumerable, careless scribes'.
Forget constructing the past from it, one can not even make 'as must as
king-lists' [1].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging the quality of contemporary historical writing in learned journals and
books is beyond me. However, it is easy to notice apathy towards history around
us. Many of Indian states are bigger than most of the European countries but a
few books are being written about what can be called their history. National
scene is only somewhat better. There is no television channel dedicated to
history worth the name. Our sense of personal history is no better. I wonder if
many Indians who can tell their family lineage which goes back more than 2-3
generations (I plead guilty).  The prominence of oral culture at the cost of
written culture for knowledge-exchange has no doubt played its part but the real
reason lies somewhere else. We do not prefer to talk about history either.
There is perhaps something in our culture which makes us indifferent to our
history. When a British born Indian historian wondered about this usual Indian
apathy towards it historical monuments, he was told by his Hindu friend, &quot;You
must understand that we are Hindus and we burn our dead.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, there is an increasing obsession with past which has little
to do with knowing the past accurately. It is largely animated by a desire to
glorify it. Tradition of dispassionate pursuit of history never had a strong
presence in India and our current value-system does not encourage it either. It
is a widely shared belief among students and their parents that history (any
form of humanities indeed) is a subject which only last on the merit-list would
take-up in school and a real loser will pick it up for a profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One needs not be a psychologist to notice the growing feelings of misery among
Indian about their nationality. This feeling is sustained by lack of coherence
and dignity in the present. Much of it also goes back to our close encounter
with western powers during colonization which humbled our traditional pride and
took away a part of our dignity. If one looks at the writings of Indian
intellectuals during this time, they were doing two things simultaneously :
telling people abroad how great things Indian are (its spirituality, its way of
life, the whole civilization indeed) and used superlatives to describe them.
Back at home they were castigating fellow-citizen for this-and-that and asking
them to change their medieval mindsets and customs. Indeed, most of the
reformers who went abroad to deliver lectures were of this kind. They painted
India as 'greatest civilization' abroad and they felt ashamed of the same
civilization's current state at home and prodded their countrymen with great
emotional appeal to change [2]. Their heirs have now started talking about India
and Bharat. They themselves belong to India which contains everything that is
good and rest of us belong to the Bharat, an unchanging and backward country for
which they only have scorn and pity. Educated people are self-consciously
virtuous everywhere, in India they are excessively so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indians are deeply conscious of being Indian. They really feel proud when a
match is won by their team, a rocket is successful launched by ISRO, a missile
is tested by DRDO, one of their movies is given or nominated for a Oscar, an
Indian buys a company abroad, a person with Indian name goes to space, and an
Indian is recognized by western world. And they flaunt this pride aggressively.
Western awards have come to mean a great deal to them. Their newspaper's global
news is all about Indians doing well abroad. The xenotrophism  -- the attraction
to the foreign, this loving (and hating) preoccupation with what Kingsley Amim
called &quot;abroad&quot; -- is to be accounted for largely by the sense of superiority of
foreign things and the inferiority of Indian things. The obsession has reached
to a level that one of our more exuberant psychologists has noted that if good
Indian and good Chinese has lived a virtuous life, they  have started going not
to heaven but to New York. Abroad has become a status-symbol and it is chased
with a great zeal. It perhaps makes them lower on their self-esteem but it helps
them stand tall is a deeply status-conscious society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who are left behind despite trying really hard develops a growing sense of
social-worthlessness and also suffer from an acute sense of inferiority. But
they are not the only one. The difference between who has left, who is about to
leave and those who could not leave can do real harm to their self-esteem.
Present and Future of India do not offer them any possibility to overcome these
feelings either.  The media and newspapers are competing with each other to
spread the feelings of misery about present and future. Their newspapers are
filled with stories telling them how pathetic is the situation is in their
country; and it has become a fashion among intelligentsia to find a crisis
everywhere. It is not entirely their fault if they feel sad, ashamed and
miserable about their homeland.  Nonetheless, they are mortified by all of this.
They see it more of an outcome of some moral deficiency rather than an outcome
of their own actions which can be changed.  This can only lead to fatalism and
the enhanced feelings of misery about being Indian itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History, especially when it is poorly documented, can be invoked with great
effect to lessen these feeling of misery. And an increasing number of Indians
are willing and even eager to be convinced of the myths of national greatness
and glory. It is a seductive myth and like all myths, when evidence in support
are lacking, they are created and easily accepted. History demands that when
evidence are lacking,  the argument must rest without a conclusion but those who
are already determined to conclude something about their past, myth and not
history offers them vast opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian civilization has many achievements to its credit and there is nothing
wrong for feeling proud about it. But when a past is invoked in India, as in
many other countries which locates their utopia in the past, it is usually to
glorify its achievements and not to speak of its failings. It is unbelievable
that any nation can have only achievements and no failing. What do they try to
achieve by brushing a nation's failings under the carpet rather than elevating
the moods? Nonetheless, those who are told of the grandeur of past also see the
misfortune of present. And it is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraphindia.com/1031011/asp/opinion/story_2433186.asp&quot;&gt;explained due
to&lt;/a&gt; 'the
intervention of colonial rule' and the plunders by ruthless attackers before
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same text-books that represent the India of the past as a land overflowing
with milk and honey also represent colonial rule as a period of relentless
plunder, spoliation and degradation.... The British were no doubt alien
intruders who disrupted a contented and harmonious way of life. But were they
the first or only intruders to do so' What our radical and liberal historians
have started is being continued further back into the past by other
historians. A recent account of the pristine greatness of India and its
spoliation by the British ends by saying that perhaps the gloom had set in
earlier, around AD 1000. Who were the bearers of this pre-British gloom' Could
they have been Afghans, or Turks' The myth of the destruction of everything
that was good in India by the British has extensions that may not all be
pleasing to those who have contributed to its making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many among us who are too willing to construct  a past where there is
only grandeur and glory and no failing. Almost all of us are too willing to
accept this version of past as the only version. It may have been a great tool
in elevating the mood of many Indians but this mood-lifting by construction of
myths is not going to do much good to them. The reasons behind this hatred may
not be easy to find or remove but these seductive myths are not going to help
remove them either [2]. However, this obsession with glorious past can easily
divert attention from the dispassionate pursuit of history. History is best
pursued by those dispassionate individuals who are driven by the curiosity to
know what they really were and not by those who are easily intoxicated by
seductive myths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References  :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] An introduction to the history of Indian history, D. D. Kosambi, pp9-10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] The intimate enemy, loss and recovery of self under colonial rule, Ashis Nandy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2013-02-04 19:46:10 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/Culture and history/2013/02/04/neglect-of-history-and-obsession-with-the-past/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Research Scholar Meetings</title>
				<description>&lt;h1&gt;WEEK 3 :&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting time : Saturday, Feb 09, 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was canceled because Prof. HN was not available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;WEEK 2 :&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting time : Saturday, Feb 02, 2013, 2.00pm onwards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week only 15-20 students turned up compared to 44 last week. It was announced that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mit.edu/~mitter/&quot;&gt;Prof. Sanjoy K. Mittar&lt;/a&gt; who is visiting the department would be interacting with students. It seems that presence of an eminent scholar did not increase their enthusiasm.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof Mittar is in his seventies and he talked slowly. He drew a sharp line between scholarship and original research. He pointed out that one can keep learning his whole life and build a scholarship but it does not necessarily lead to original research. I am not sure if he put a larger value on original research. Prof Narayanan quoted a line from a poem which he read in his school. This line is 'to see the world in grain of sand' which he interpreted, 'do a small problem and do it thoroughly and one would learn a great deal about other things'. Prof. Mittar also suggested that one should prefer to pursue one's Ph. D. in a field which is less crowded. Perhaps, so that there is more scope for creativity. He also made a distinction between science and engineering. While the former is about discovering the fundamental limits, the later is concerned about maximum limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Mittar has a line of research. He emphasized that IITs must engage themselves on the national problem as MIT has been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked him whether he sees a difference between intellectual cultures of India and US or IIT Bombay and MIT. He made a point that IIT Bombay surely can not hope to replicate the resources MIT has but there are certain areas where IIT Bombay can work effectively. He was not sure whether it answered my question and I replied in negative. Of course, I had to explain my point of view and sociologists are notorious for not able to make their point in nutshell. I mentioned that my point of view is usually the point of view of sociology (HN chuckled) which studies how the cultures (or the habit of hearts) define the way an individual acts. We compare and contrast. Therefore I was curious if he noted something in our culture compared to US culture which can act against doing research. This discussion lead into another direction which I terminated. He asked whether I want to be a sociologist. I did not rule out the possibility. He mentioned light heartedly if I knew that sociology is in crisis. 'Well, they say there is a crisis everywhere these days', was my answer to it. He smiled and suggested as one can also define crisis. I found him to be a very generous, kind-hearted and down-to-earth man. It was nice to have him in our meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind reduction of number of students joining the meeting is not very clear to me this time. Whatever is the reason behind it, it has to be conceded that we do not put very high value on such meetings. Of course, they can be inspired and encouraged to join but it does not contradict the hypothesis that their natural inclination (or habit of hearts as I'd like to phrase such things) is not for such discussion. This is not to say that this can be changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such discussion, where students exchange ideas with each others and suggest some probable solutions to one's problem, are great facilitator of research in any academic institute. And we have a poor record in such discussion in our department. We have enthusiasm for starting magazines and start-up. These magazines and start-up do not survive for long but they are a great thing to be put on one's resume. I have heard one undergraduate complaining that the reason behind such startup is to get admission to London School of Economics. I can't vouch how much truth is there in this assertion but it is not entirely false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magazines or newsletters can be a by-product of discussions, it can not replace discussions altogether. Most of the great research institutes are there where they are these days because they had this tradition of building groups where people put great values on such a culture. Students can not be faulted for this. This is prevalent among faculty in our universities (our department has good record when it comes to the tradition 'talking with each other'). They divide themselves into factions, euphemistically called 'like minded intellectuals'.  Now we have more number of students on the department but on feels that Prof. Betteille is right when he observed that while our universities 'proliferated and grew in size', but could no longer 'conform to the original concept of a self-governing community of scholars — they are neither self-governing nor do they have a sense of community or scholarship.'&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I wish to look forward to study in following meetings is that whether they are showing a growing sense of community of scholarship (or original research as its byproduct).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;WEEK 1 :&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Harihar Narayanan (HN) retired last month from Electrical Engineering Department. He has been be at the center of student mentor-ship program for undergraduates at institute level. I believe that he had some success with academically poor undergraduates. And since department has tried hard to retain him for few more years as adjunct-professor, he plans to devote one day each week to mentor department’s research scholars. Each Saturday we will meet to discuss this-and-that. This is a great opportunity for me as a sociologist to do some field work as participant-observer. And to get some taste of social life also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last meeting, there were around 44 PhD students, mainly from EE and some from CSE department. Few of them were new students but mainly they were senior Ph. D. students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He likes to talk and feels rejuvenated after giving a good lecture. It was not easy for him but he tried hard not to make this discussion monologue. He encouraged students to point out problems and to offer suggestions and comments for the department. Many of them are listed below. Not in the same form they were uttered by the students, he generalized many of them. It was a moderated session and a senior faculty was present. Therefore many of these comments and complains are very mild compared to what they usually complain to their peers. The Indian habit of ‘comparing everything with the worst’ is not visible. There is a good chance that something useful will come out of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complaints&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research (in India?) driven by publication rather than originality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not always `relevant’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;PhD students dont work hard. (No one complained about it, this one he put on board by himself).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Little or no office space.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;TA duties not always spelled out clearly and workload is not shared properly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How to make learning/exploration enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a student is interested in a topic other than the allotted one. (On this he talks for a while. He suggested to steer the problem according to your interest)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggestions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Should be a balance between theoretical and practical work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originality should be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maths dept should be bigger!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There should be more intra/inter department interaction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Social interaction with faculty/guide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crash courses by PhD students within and outside dept.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;More interaction with external world (It was suggested that they should also teach in engineering colleges. It will help them to learn and also to earn some money.).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How to make all students flourish simultaneously? (He generalized some other suggestion)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mentoring should be its own reward (He strongly emphasized on it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was surprising no-one complain about the amount of money they are getting during their Ph.D.. This is a major concerns shown by students who leave India for higher studies (I myself has heard students saying it many times). I am not sure money is the only thing they will miss if they remain they India. But they like to point it out forcefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end, he asked student to write small autobiography to be submitted in the next meeting. This autobiography will be confidential. He stressed that autobiography should contain likes and dislikes and strengths and weaknesses as perceived by students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also asked students to come prepared with their topics (where applicable) and present to smaller groups first (5- 10 minute presentations) say 10 in each group (60-70 mins). They must cut out jargon so that talk should be understandable to an educated layman.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2013-02-02 22:05:06 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/About a person/IIT Bombay/2013/02/02/research-scholar-meeting-week-2/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Criticism and Witch-hunt</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our newspapers are filled with articles and news-reports where all sorts of accusations and allegations can be found. People in India, like people in many other countries, were not any less enthusiastic in the past for lashing out at their politicians, bureaucrats or any public-office holder but the style and content of this activity has been changed greatly by Internet and media. It is more common these days to find people accusing not only public figures but also their colleagues for some wrong or corrupt conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Criticism is an important intellectual activity and it is desirable that a society takes a critical view of itself. Criticism can take many forms and some of them can be destructive in long run. It is all to good if people in a society are critical in sober and constructive ways. Their are ample scope for other forms of criticism too such as polemic, satire etc. My intention here is to point out some forms of criticism which can easily take a destructive form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One form of criticism is whistle-blowing where a corrupt practices of a colleague is brought out in public. Usually the whistle-blower belongs to the same institute. Tradition of whistle-blowing is perhaps a healthy tradition in long run for it keeps the rot in an institute in check. But there is more to it. Whistle-blowing is most effective when it is done in the interest of institute for purposes such as maintaining ethical standards. But those who do it not always motivated by the desire to maintain ethical standard for ethical standards can also be maintained by internal censure effectively. Whistle-blowing is mostly if not always done to settle personal scores. And it can scare people to avoid taking decisions which can easily be painted as wrong decisions. Here if nothing to expose, an honest mistake or any decision can be presented as corrupt practice. A charge can also be fabricated out of imagination. And it is naive to believe that those who are labeled as politicians are the only one who do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, there has been a constant tirades against government by civil society, a term which is not easy to define. When trust is low between state and people, people like to believe in anything, not only against the government but also against whole state machinery. Sooner or later it becomes a habit, a sort of fashion, to accuse government even when evidences in support are lacking. To give an example : one social activists &lt;a href=&quot;http://zeenews.india.com/news/nation/team-anna-smells-govt-conspiracy-behind-power-failure_790587.html&quot;&gt;accused government of conspiracy&lt;/a&gt; when northern-grid failed and there was a blackout. Those who have read about the emergency in India during Indira Gandhi rule will find a great deal of similarities between her habit of making conspiracy theories about a western hand trying to do some harm to the integrity of India. Nationality of this hand was always in doubts or never revealed but its color was believed to be white.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of it can be understood and explained in terms of lack of trust between citizens and governments. But what about people, even those with nothing against each other, are picking up this tradition of criticism and arguments. Visit any newspaper's unmoderated discussion threads (such as Times of India) or Facebook groups; one sees little enthusiasm for constructive dialogue. They love to get personal and accuse each other for being timid, morally corrupt or stupid or all of it. It is curious that even those who are very polite and considerate off-line can get so caustic and aggressive on-line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central idea behind any healthy tradition of argument is to play the ball and not the man. But when the activity of arguments is confused with entertainment, it must be very hard for them to resist the temptation to have some fun by playing the man. Indians love to have different opinions and they tend to be very argumentative. They find it very hard to consider different positions and agree with any of them but their own, especially during a debate. A Canadian diplomat has observed rather light-heartedly that in India the challenge is 'to get people agree with you even if they do' while in China 'the challenge is to get people disagree with you, even if they do'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the rants one hears almost every day is that [almost] everyone in India is corrupt, stupid or selfish. It should not be hard to show that all people, even most of them, are not corrupt or perverse in a society. For if they were so that particular society would have met an evil fate long ago. But proving a fact is one thing and caught in the feelings is another. In a society where someone accuses everyone else of some wrongdoing or having an evil character or both, it is not unnatural for people to develop feelings that being so must be the natural state of their society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there is a lot of hidden energy in our society which has not been explored properly and systematically. This energy not only works against any critical view of Indian society, it is often used against individuals trying to do harmless things. If someone is participating in the classroom then he has to face comments like 'Sala, trying to be smart!' or some scornful faces after the class. If someone is writing posts on a discussion group then he must be motivated by reasons not entirely laudable. If someone has shown some concerns about a scientist seeking blessing from a petty god-man for the successful launch of satellite then 'it is the usual shenanigans' on his part. If a teaching assistant has not given 10 out of 10 marks then he has to responds to emails justifying his decision. If a professor has supported LAN ban in IIT Bombay then he must be driven by some ill-feeling against students or perversity. And if the director of an IIT has supported government's reforms (or changes) in IIT-JEE then the director of some other IIT accuse him of having 'hidden agenda' and “irresistible urge to manage other IITs'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been passing through a phase in which every disorder is explained by the irrational belief of every kind : a secret hand, a hidden conspiracy, an evil personality. This is partly because the habit of thinking clearly and rationally about the social condition around oneself takes time to become established among people ( I often felt how hard it is). This way of looking at social order responsible for personal or public misfortunes is a modern one, even in those societies where it was preached first. And it demands a great deal of isolation of mind from moral-excitement and passions of all sorts. Such a habit and intellectual discipline associated with it has not acquired a strong foothold in our society, even among intelligentsia. And those who can lay foundation of such a culture -- newspapers and magazines -- are now acting against it. Moreover, our own traditional intellectual culture lends itself easily to fatalism : either a fatalistic acceptance of the existing order of the thing or a fatalistic withdrawal from the concerns of this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only the lack of intellectual habits and presence of abundant energy hostile to anything odd, critical or different in outlook causing damage to our intellectual culture but also a growing taste for what can be compared with witch-hunting in medieval Europe. This is most visible on our news channels which are now competing with entertainment industries. And it is trickling down to the connected masses. These are secular forms of witch-hunting and it grows rapidly in certain kind of social environment : when people believe that it is some hidden hand or some evil personality and not some social-construct or collectivities which are responsible for the misfortune. It is most unfortunate that any society develops a taste for it. It spreads with and spreads cynicism. Anthropologists have studied witch-hunting for a long time and concluded that it is the most dangerous social-construct ever invented by man-kind. For it deranged accused and accuser alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2013-01-30 15:18:32 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/India/Indian Culture/Indian Media/2013/01/30/criticism-and-witch-hunting/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>In praise of : Secularism </title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A growing tendency in India is to attack secularism, covertly and indirectly. The attack on secularism is somewhat similar to the attack on equality. They maintain since we can not define secularism (like equality) in a strict sense, it will be good if we stop using the term altogether, at least to avoid the intellectual confusion. More adventurous among them will go on to say that it does not exists at all and everything which is called secular is a form of pseudo-secular. &lt;!-- more --&gt;In addition, they may also argue that many people those who speak in the name of the secularism are not strictly secular. Similarly, as one would say against equality, all those who speaks in the name of equality do not practice equality. Indeed, one can easily show that many of them practice in private just opposite of what they preach in public. But can we take these inconsistencies in the practices of these secularists against the idea of secularism itself? It yes, then it is easy to show that those who maintain that religion is a good thing often use it to achieve some other ends. Then, it is pseudo-religion which exists and therefore we must stop using the term altogether? We can drive a term to a logical nihilism but it will be a counsel of despair. Besides a meaning has to be given to secularism, even if it does not exists in strict sense for it has made its way into our constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at various concrete definitions of secularism then one can raise many serious doubts about it. In an engaging book, Amartya Sen has listed out six major criticism of secularism. They are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Non-existent critique, 2. The 'Favouritism' critique, 3. The 'Prior Identity' critique, 4. The 'Muslim Sectarianism' critique, 5. The 'Anti-Modernist' critique, 6. The 'Cultural' Critique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And he goes on to defend secularism. Amartya Sen's ability to make distinctions is amazing and he moves from one distinction to another at the breathtaking speed. I can not possibly give an overview of all of these distinctions in this post. I'd suggest that you read the essay 'Secularism and its discontents' [in the book The argumentative Indian] by yourself. What I wish to do in this post, however, is to give a sociological perspective to the idea of secularism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If secularism is an ideology then like all ideologies it must stand for something. And those who stands for something have to stand against something else. Ideologies try to change the word and to change the world, they must pursue power. Therefore if secularism is an ideology, then it must take away the power from something and give it to itself. Is it religion?  The common definitions of secularism are dependent on religion and it generates a feeling of as if the spread of secularism will ultimately displace the religion from the public life. Therefore who are for religion must be anti-secular and vice versa. This view is not satisfactory. In sociology, many of us maintain that secularism does not necessarily work against religion. It does not eliminate religion from society or even reduce its influence on individuals. It brings out some places out of the grips of the religion such as universities, hospitals, banks, offices etc. With the spread of secularization, there will be more places in society where religion cease to play any [significant] part. To give an example, a modern hospital and a modern university are such places where religion does not play any visible role. Religion, on these institutes, is a private thing for its member. And it is very hard to see how these institutes can work efficiently, if they can work at all, if they were to be governed by religious than secular rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is religious pluralism is a form of secularism or perhaps it's  most exalted form as it is increasingly maintained in India? India has a good record in religion pluralism and tolerance. But it must not be forgotten that it has some dark spots too. There is a great deal of sympathy for minorities in our intellectual circles. Indeed, some of the most unreasonable demands made my minorities are not only tolerated, they are often encouraged. One of such demand was made by Muslims for reservation recently. A few centuries ago, their proud forefathers were the rulers of  most of these lands. Therefore it does not follow that they are left behind simply because majority has denied something to them. At least not in the way in which high castes Hindus had denied certain rights to many low castes Hindus and women. It has to be said in all fairness that it was also high caste Hindus above everyone else who attacked the foundation of caste system most vigorously. It is worthwhile to note in passing what Dr. Ambedkar said on this, 'It is wrong for the majority to deny the existence of minorities. It is equally wrong for minorities to perpetuate themselves.' One of the criticism of secularism is based on these feelings that secularism helps minorities to perpetuate themselves :  'appeasement of minorities' as it is often called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;'Dharam nirpekhshta' or 'religious plurality' can do some of the work assigned to secularism, but it can not do all of it. Consider a country where there is only one religion i.e. a Christian country of Europe. In this country admission to university was granted to those men who subscribed to a certain church and it was denied to all women. It was secular forces and not 'religious pluralism' which opened the gate of universities to women. And in India, Hindu or Muslim religion are not particularly kind to many castes and women. If people from lower castes are allowed these days to vote or allowed to go to universities and seek employment in those professions which were not assigned to them at birth, and women are allowed to go to temples during their periods, it is due to secularization of society and not due to religious tolerance or religious plurality. Secularism is a modern value and it a new value even in those countries where it found its first adherents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a university man and wish to be on an university for rest of my life. My whole existence depends on the fact that my university governed by secular rules. How can I ever ask secularism to leave even when I find that a great many things are being done in its name are against its spirit. And those who ask secularism to leave must also ask themselves how their life would have been if the institutions they are part of were to be governed by religious rules. They must carefully consider what they are abandoning and what they are asking others to abandon by abandoning secularism. If secularism has to go, a great many things which are essential to life of mind must also go. To the opponents of secularism, it would make them less anxious if they see it as a 'habit of heart' rather than an ideology. As a habit of heart, it will cease to be anti-religion. It will only asks people what Jesus is believed to ask his fellows, 'Render unto Caesar the things which are Caesar's, and unto God the things that are God's'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--
Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;Related articles&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dilawars.wordpress.com/2013/01/21/secularism-re-examined/&quot;&gt;Secularism re-examined : By Andre Beteille&lt;/a&gt; (dilawars.wordpress.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dilawars.wordpress.com/2012/12/10/religious-identities/&quot;&gt;Religious Identities&lt;/a&gt; (dilawars.wordpress.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.secularnewsdaily.com/2012/11/poll-shows-turks-want-secularism/&quot;&gt;Poll shows Turks want secularism&lt;/a&gt; (secularnewsdaily.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2013-01-27 13:25:14 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/In Praise Of/Indian Society/2013/01/27/in-praise-of-secularism/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>In praise of : Ashis Nandy</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Nandy_ashis.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/49/Nandy_ashis.jpg/75px-Nandy_ashis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;English: Ashis Nandy, receiving the Fukuoka As...&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;To one of his admirers, no less than a Ramachandra Guha, Ashis Nandy is 'an unclassifiable social scientist'. To me, who has an impressionable young mind, he is capable of giving few sleepless nights. He mixes psychology and philosophy with sociology to a magical effect. I can not imagine anyone who would read him without being deeply influenced. His collection of essays '&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Intimate-Enemy-Recovery-Under-Colonialism/dp/0195622375%3FSubscriptionId%3D0G81C5DAZ03ZR9WH9X82%26tag%3Dzemanta-20%26linkCode%3Dxm2%26camp%3D2025%26creative%3D165953%26creativeASIN%3D0195622375&quot;&gt;The intimate enemy&lt;/a&gt;' (and other works too) have decolonized some minds. His work continues to have a deep impact on South Asian intellectual culture. He is surely one of the finest public intellectuals of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't comment much on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tirchhispelling.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A5%8B-%E0%A4%86%E0%A4%B6%E0%A5%80%E0%A4%B7-%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%82%E0%A4%A6%E0%A5%80-%E0%A4%8F%E0%A4%95-%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A4%E0%A5%8D/&quot;&gt;merit of his&lt;/a&gt; work but I can comment something on his intellectual temperament. I prefer people who has the intellectual temperament of a naturalist : someone who is interested in finding things out for himself above everything else. He is definitely more than that. To be sure, he is deeply interested in 'interpreting the world' , but he also interested in changing it for he do judgment of values and distinguish things between right and wrong. Moreover he loves to surprise and edify his readers. Perhaps this is why his email id starts with 'reasonbuster'. Exuberant intellectuals often stretch the point and they mislead their readers, sometimes knowingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His writings are very ambitious in scope. He establishes connections among seemingly unconnected things and he moves from one conclusion to another at a great speed. He questions and attacks, perhaps religiously, well-established wisdom. The little magazine has called him the best known voice of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a great admirer of Prof. &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andre_B%C3%A9teille&quot;&gt;Andre Beteille&lt;/a&gt;. I am perhaps the youngest engineer alive in this world to do so. I learnt it from him that an intellectual pursuit is, above everything else,  to scratch the surface of confusion caused by observation and experience. It is 'a slow boring of hard boards', to borrow a phrase of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Max_Weber&quot;&gt;Max Weber&lt;/a&gt;. I have always gotten carried away by Nandy till I read what he wrote in the preface of  collection of his well-known essays, 'I shall not grudge it if some enterprising reviewer finds unconvincing history in the following pages, as long as he finds in them convincing myths.'  and somewhere else in an essay '.. the way to fight the myth : by building of resurrecting more convincing myths.' I am not sure if he still hold these beliefs. If he does, he and his reader would do well to remember that a sociologist, a historian, or any intellectual does not create myths.  They produce enough raw material from which other produces them. And they oughtn't create myths even when they are not expected to take any responsibility for their creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epw.in/authors/ashis-nandy&quot;&gt;Nandy in EPW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medialabju.org/omeka/items/show/40&quot;&gt;Woman vs womanliness in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;Related articles&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraphindia.com/1130129/jsp/opinion/story_16492475.jsp&quot;&gt;nandy's nadir&lt;/a&gt; (telegraphindia.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kafila.org/2013/01/30/ashis-nandys-predicament-and-ours/&quot;&gt;Ashis Nandy's Predicament and Ours&lt;/a&gt; (kafila.org)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2012-12-18 02:05:38 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/About a person/In Praise Of/2012/12/18/in-praise-of-ashis-nandy/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>An open letter to IIT undergraduates</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your IITian-ness,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may not be conscious of it but your appetite for comparison and self-congratulation if not narcissism is colossal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I understand that success in competitive examinations boosts one's confidence and increases one's pride in one's abilities. If this pride drives you to hone your intellectual abilities and professional skills further so you can be among the best in your game, then anyone can hardly have anything against it. It is good to be proud for people who do not feel proud of themselves often feel miserable and easily give into self-hatred. Self-hatred is not only an inimical personal trait, it can hardly contribute anything meaningful to society. You must preserve the pride, no matter how misplaced it is. It is not easy to feel proud in this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for some of you, the success in JEE is nothing less than a certificate of being a superior life form. A certificate that your thing is bigger than mine. This is irritating. The brand which you call 'IITians' and wear it like your last name is nothing&lt;a href=&quot;http://dilawarrajput.wordpress.com/2013/02/20/heirarchy-and-status-a-sociological-perpective-on-caste-brand-for-life-iitian/&quot;&gt; less than a caste like Brahmin&lt;/a&gt; for it allows one to speak of oneself in superlatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experiences in IIT Bombay tell me that as far as engineering is concerned, average among you is better than the average among us. And I concede that our jerks are bigger jerks than your jerks. But is it too hard to see your Dudeness that your finest are nowhere near to our finest? You have not produced your equivalents of a Bose, a Raman, a Saha, a Vishveshvarraya, a Beteille, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palagummi_Sainath&quot;&gt;Sainath&lt;/a&gt;, a Ramachardra Guha, an &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irawati_Karve&quot;&gt;Irawati Karve&lt;/a&gt;, a Kalam , a CNR Rao. And if you are among those who prefer greenbacks over gray-cells (like most of us), then look at the number of richest people in India (you can refer to Forbes list). Compute the ratio or non-IITian and IITians. It must not be hard for you. You rule among the averages and we rule at the extremes at both ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll give it a serious thought before you go around again comparing your penis with mine. Have fun comparing with each others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wishing you a productive life [abroad] !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;Related articles&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dilawarrajput.wordpress.com/2012/06/26/concern-with-jee-merit-etc-in-iits/&quot;&gt;Concern with JEE, merit etc in IITs&lt;/a&gt; (dilawarrajput.wordpress.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dilawarrajput.wordpress.com/2013/02/20/heirarchy-and-status-a-sociological-perpective-on-caste-brand-for-life-iitian/&quot;&gt;Heirarchy and status : A sociological perpective on ‘caste (brand for life) IITian’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2012-12-16 09:16:31 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/IIT Bombay/Open Letter/2012/12/16/an-open-letter-to-iit-undergraduate/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Academic dishonesty</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I have been a teaching assistant in IIT Bombay since 2007. In otherwise a continuous stint, there was a gap of one year when I worked in industry after completing my masters. I prefer programming and lab related courses. I take a perverse interest in figuring out which student has copied his/her assignment. There have been many instances of cheating in those courses; and my intention is to comment on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of our professors who does not mince words in classroom and is reputed to be a very hard-working person (not just by local standards), remarked once in the classroom that when someone cheats, he is essentially saying that he is incompetent. 'Why would anyone cheat or import if he can do it by himself', he wondered. He went on to say that this applies to individuals as well as to nations. This is definitely true in its own context. I know some students who were technically weak but did not cheat and those who were sharp and technically sound but did not mind cheating when they got half a chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my M. Tech., I was close to a group of undergraduates. I found them to be sharp and clever; one of them was perhaps brilliant. They were usually well-behaved, even in their private spaces. Although their behavior on 'profile-reading' was like that of a drunkard in my village during Holi. I remember going to their hostel once and finding out that one of them calling another one 'chutiya' while others were looking at him with amusement. It turned out that in a lab examination, they all were in the corner cheating and the 'chutiya' among them refused to be a part of this activity. That an individual refusing to be a part of his peer group activity, which he thought to be unethical, is rare in our style of society. It is also natural that a group ridicules a member of it who does not take part in its activities, evil or benign. But one expects a group of students to be more tolerant of a 'black sheep'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No doubt that cheating is beneficial in short run and there are certain temptations, with some reason, to indulge in it. But we can not ignore the fact that we live in a society which tolerates such dishonesty to a great extent. All individual pursue their interest, not always consciously, but it is a mistake to believe that all of them pursue their interests at any cost at most of the time. What stands out is the gall of this group to contemptuously ridicule one of their member who did not pursue those benefits at the cost of his dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How cheating is perceived and how it is defined varies individual to individual . What seems to be a case of cheating to some may not look like a case of cheating at all to many others. Still, it is possible for an academic community to define what constitute as unethical practice and to expect from its members to honor the code. The best way to maintain such standards is internal censure. When this internal censure weakens, dishonesty increases. Copy and paste in seminar reports submitted by our students are rampant and it is tolerated to great extent. Last year in a panel discussion 'what is research' a professor remarked, 'there have been cases of plagiarism in Ph. D. thesis.' It was also tolerated because they didn't 'want to appear on the front page of Times of India.' This is odd; to admit at one hand that they can not maintain some basic ethical standards for fears real or imagined and to demand more autonomy on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless pointed out in great clarity, many of students caught cheating would not like to see it academic dishonesty; partly due to ignorance and partly to avoid accusation of being corrupt. Who likes to see himself a moral cripple? Therefore they devise ingenuous arguments in their defense. I do not know many supporting it in public without giving one reason or another. 'Everyone does it' is one of such reason they usually give to their peers. It will not be hard to prove that not everyone, or even most of the people, in this society are cheater. But proving a fact is one thing and caught in a feeling is another. In a society where everyday someone accuses everyone else of some wrongdoing, it is not all very unnatural for people to believe that being so must be the natural state of their society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know at least one Teaching Assistant who was making a case to the instructor, who was also her guide, in favor of such students. She argued that usually there is a 'lack of time' to complete these assignments therefore it is natural for these people to 'do-what-they-have-done'. I suspect that there would be many others with similar opinions. Her guide was not convinced about it but he was of view that punishment should not be very severe for 'all in the IIT do it'. There is definitely some element of truth in the insinuation that 'all of them do it' but I also suspect that Indian mind is prone to compare everything with the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of time can hardly be  an acceptable argument. That particular instructor has mentioned may times in the classroom that if someone is having difficulty in assignments, he should approach him. Besides why do they not submit a partial assignment? There is a very thin line between 'discussing with friends' and cheating and this line is often transgressed. This need not be the case, but this is the usual experience. The 'lack of time' argument for cheating is no more convincing that the argument our academicians often put forward for not honoring their teaching commitments i.e. they have to spend a lot of time in meetings and committees. And they have their strikes to attend too. As far as students are considered, this reason sits oddly with my personal experiences. These time-starved students spend an unusual amount of their time in being social butterfly. I do not remember many times when I did not see a hostel room either empty or occupied by more than one person chatting, watching movies, chit-chatting with unusual amount of laughter. Doing individual assignments is a solitary activity. Spending time in solitude does not come naturally to an Indian who is extremely gregarious by nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temptation to get as many marks as possible by fair of foul means aside, there is perhaps a conviction -- consolidated by past experiences and with some reason -- that they can get away with it; especially when they belong to a majority. This is perhaps the reason a cheater usually start his case by saying 'everyone does it' and try to pull the weight of numbers on his side. In a society where constitutional morality is low and foundation of institutes are weak, 'rule of number' often prevails over 'rule of law'.  As of the temptation of cheating, promotion of brutal competition has its own cost for it can create a society which is callous and self-serving. In such a society, skills such as leadership, gardening, art, empathy, honesty, and desire to help each other etc. counts for little. [see, The rise of meritocracy, Micheal Young]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should universities or any institutes punish these family members? There can be many arguments for it (and some against it). It is naive to believe that those who are doing it are merely a 'victim of system or society' or doing it due to 'lack or time'; they know what they are doing and they seem to know it very well. They are doing it to fetch rewards at the cost of their profession and institute, and perhaps at the cost of their colleagues too. Sympathy for young aside, they are greatly tolerated by faculty because they themselves have breathed the same air which their students are breathing now. Even if we accept that these students are merely acting under one illusion or other, there is a limit to which a university should tolerate them. These students may not care for their own reputation and dignity, but when the dirty linen comes out in public it irreparably damage the reputation and dignity of the institute. Their will be a demand for outside censure; and it would be hard to deny even by those who are all for academic autonomy. An academic community must convince itself of the importance of a strong internal censor. And if the  academic community is inwardly convinced that this is not a serious issue then such an institute must have an evil fate. Lack of competence may not force people to cheat, but those who cheat religiously not only have parasitic characters, they are often very incompetent people. No institute can survive, let alone flourish, without a competent and dignified academic community which does not live up to even basic academic standards and ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;END NOTES :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scribd.com/doc/116599290/Prof-H-Narayanan-on-personal-ethics&quot;&gt;[1] : Prof. H Narayanan on personal ethics&lt;/a&gt;[2] Stuyvesant Students Describe the How and the Why of Cheating, A news report. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/26/education/stuyvesant-high-school-students-describe-rationale-for-cheating.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;_r=0&quot;&gt;The New York Times, Sep 25, 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;Related articles&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dilawarrajput.wordpress.com/2012/05/19/life-on-a-campus-iit-bombay/&quot;&gt;Life on a campus : IIT Bombay&lt;/a&gt; (dilawarrajput.wordpress.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://acculturated.com/2012/10/01/the-culture-of-cheating/&quot;&gt;The culture of cheating&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lugenfamilyoffice.com/2012/11/24/rsa-animate-the-truth-about-dishonesty/&quot;&gt;RSA Animate: The Truth About Dishonesty&lt;/a&gt; (lugenfamilyoffice.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2012-12-12 21:25:22 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/IIT Bombay/Indian Culture/2012/12/12/academic-dishonesty/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Society's perception of woman</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;That men do cruel things to women is widely acknowledged and accepted. What is often concealed, not always in innocence, is that woman cruelty towards woman is no less compared to men's cruelty to women. This is not to condone any sort of violence to anyone but to draw attention to a fact. It has been pointed out that most of the female fetus abandoned or killed in India are due maternal neglect. Moreover, those who persuade or force mother to abandon a girl child; the doctor or the dai who does these operations are usually woman. This is a weird but strong statement on women hostility towards womanhood. This is also a classic case of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defence_mechanism&quot;&gt;psychological defense mechanism&lt;/a&gt; in which the victim starts identifying with his or her aggressor and turned against himself or herself. It needs attention to the ways in which social institutes turn men and women against womenhood. And the purpose of this post to scratch the surface of this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feminists have given a new dimensions to issues related to women. There are many feminists with genuine concerns for the misfortunes and sympathy for women. There are also many among them who are driven by sheer misandry. The early days of feminism was shaped by some of the most remarkable women. 'I myself have never been able to find out precisely what feminism is', the writer Rebecca West remarked rather sardonically in 1913. 'I only know that people call me a feminist whenever I express sentiments that differentiate me from a doormat or a prostitute.'  [5] In India, feminist view has mostly been a human point of view : the rights of women are human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To radical feminists, any issue between a man and a woman is an issue between men and women. 'The cruelty done to woman', they argue, that it is either done by men directly or by design. Their work are useful for comparison of point of view. There are enough evidence that men play prominent role in constant tutelage of women but women too do many self-derogatory thing to themselves. I can not comment on psychological reasons for women turning against themselves. In most of traditional patriarchal societies, woman are believed to have fickle and aggressive sexual nature. The belief had been, though the no one will speak implicitly in its favor, that they will have intercourse with someone if given half a change. Their mobility was restricted. This mindset makes itself visible on televisions, most vividly in men's vest and perfumes ads. A few decades ago, some concerns were raised about &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexual_objectification&quot;&gt;objectification of women&lt;/a&gt; in media. One reason for this malaise was offered : media is controlled by men. Now we have many females executive and presenters in media houses and news rooms; can we say that objectification of women is reduced in newspapers and magazines? The point is simple, women in advantaged positions can collude with men, their so called oppressor, and turn against themselves.Indian women are of subservient nature and they are known to accept their place in society. This is not to say they always accept their place by choice. There is a grand theory which justifies and elaborates place for women in our society. Even in most modern section of our society, nobody really knows the theory of pollution and purity but practice usually outlive its theory. It is only recently that women have started criticizing these patriarchal designs and have started breaking the traditional norms, including perhaps the good one. The whole society seems to be hostile towards these women. EPW, the keeper of nation's conscience, sums the situation up in one of its editorial after the 'horrific sexual assault on a teenage girl on the streets of Guwahati on 9 July'. The 'assault will not be forgotten for a long time', it says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;because of the nature of the crime, where the young woman was dragged away from the auto rickshaw which she was about to take and surrounded by a mob of more than 20 men who punched her, tore off her clothes, pulled her hair, groped her, burnt her with cigarette butts, called her a prostitute – everything short of a gang rape. Not only because of the shockingly slow response of the police located just one kilometre away. Not only because of the crass and callous indifference of dozens of citizens who drove past the girl as she ran down the street screaming for help. Not only because of the scandalous and unforgivable act of ­revealing the identity of the girl by the representative of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Commission_for_Women&quot;&gt;National Commission for Women&lt;/a&gt;, Alka Lamba. Or the equally mindless action of the Assam chief minister’s publicity department of sending to the media photographs of the girl with the chief minister.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual violence is an extreme form which day to day tutelage can take. A sexual of physical assault done by group is different than an assault by individual. During wars and riots, rape is mostly done as an act of punishment or for 'teaching a lesson' and to break the spirit of the enemy; and it continues to be so in many places. Before any violence can be done, an individual or a group must convince itself that the victim is not equally human. That he or she has done something for which he or she should be punished. This is a society where law punishes even those who try to commit suicide. As Bertrand Russel has noted, &quot;the infliction of cruelty with a good conscience is a delight to moralists. That is why they invented Hell.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian men have deep feelings of ambivalence towards women. And why those who are immensely polite towards them (many of our leaders during the time of independence) keep a safe emotional distance from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violence_against_women&quot;&gt;Violence towards women&lt;/a&gt; is common in all societies; although male violence towards woman is widely recorded by feminists in their respective societies. A psychologist reports 'disturbing evidence' form U.S. from various studies. 'One-quarter of American women will experience a completed rape at some time in their lives, and nearly one half will be victims of attempted or completed rape. Since the age of 14, 27.5% of college women have experienced an attempted or completed rape.' Each year, approximately '1.8 million American wives are beaten by their husbands and one-eighth of all murders involve husbands killing their wives.' And situation is India is likely to be severe because patriarchy is much deeply rooted and incidence or rape or domestic violence are hugely under-reported due to one social pressure or other.Studies by anthropologists have concluded that men violence towards woman is a universal feature of humanity. Although the prevalence of male violence against women varies from place to place, 'cross-cultural surveys show that societies in which men rarely attack or rape women are the exception, not the norm'. It is said the 'male sexual jealousy is the most common trigger for wife beating.' I think this is what Freud called 'penis envy' although &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.littlemag.com/venusenvy/index.html&quot;&gt;'The Little Magazine' &lt;/a&gt;differs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher gender-inequality does not help containing these violence. Where women do not have access to property or income, she is more like to suffer in silence, or more likely to use methods to survive which undermines her dignity and self-esteem as a human being. Gender inequality is not an easy thing to define or elaborate. There are measurable inequality attached to it such as distribution of property, illiteracy, access to food and nutrition, marriage age etc.; on the other hand there are many immeasurable yet important inequalities such as self-esteem, access to legal institutes, and dignity etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the most basis level there is evolutionary tension : male tries to benefit by mating with any female whereas female do not benefit mating with every male comes her way. This tension is becomes very severe in those primates where male do not provide any parental care. Among mammals, a gender which invest heavily in its offspring tends to be more choosy. Usually females invest more and therefore they are more choosy. Males either compete for them or mate with them forcibly. For a detailed commentary on 'male aggression towards women' among primates can be found in [1]. Many social arrangements must have been constructed in response to this evolutionary tension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychology of sexual violence &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregory Zilboorg famous paper suggests something similar. Male oppression of women emanates from his attempts to deny his deepest anxiety. 'The most socially valued attribute of the male', Zilborg argues, is a 'result of natural selection imposed upon him by the female's original power; which is to sense which male is biologically fitter for her offspring'. According to Steven Pinker, human females prefer 'dark and dashing heroes' (for better genes for their offspring) for short term affairs while 'caring and nurturing one' (for better resources and nourishment for their offspring) for long term relation. It is likely that caring and nurturing 'dad' who is no less prone to fall in love with a woman, develops a feeling of hate towards women when he faces rejection for a dark and dashing 'clad'. How a woman evaluates such attributes in a male is altogether different matter. In society like us, women often prefer males who can provide better security and status in her society. Those who rely heavily on self-assessment, may pick someone with high IQ or EQ or other skills which they value, even though they are not high in status or profitable in markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women dominate in mate-selection process and this supremacy of women arouse a feeling of jealousy and hostility towards women [3]. In certain western countries where males were reduced to a very small number due to world war, women have to learn to compete for better men. In India, however, situation has always been different. It is the male who is in excess and it is the male who often tries to woo a better (read beautiful) woman. Indians women usually don't like to take the first step for the fear of considered 'immoral' or 'cheaply available'. Girls who are beautiful and attractive often attracts a great deal of unwanted attention and jealously which is best noticed in the comments passed by a group of boys when they see a girl with some other boy :  such as 'aajkal is laudiye' (Girls these days ....'). What stands out in this often passed comment is that they insinuate something about whole gender after seeing a girl which does not fit to their image of proper girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of our intellectuals, whether Left wing or Right wing, agree on one thing while discussing why Indian cities, and perhaps even villages, have become insecure for our women : it is an outcome of modernity. Modernity may have consolidated hatred and angers towards [some type of] women; it has not created those feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modernity is a new phenomenon in India. And when an old system is being changed by a new one, it is not going to be a painless process. We are an agriculture society and an agriculture society have a love-hate relationship with nature and such societies tends to emphasize 'feminine principle in nature, to see nature as mother who is irascible and unpredictable, pro-pitiable only through a variety of rites and rituals' [2]. In our past, nature played a dominant part in the man-nature dyad and continues to do so; 'important themes in folklore and religious text are often speak of the fecundity and bounty of nature as well as her frequent denial of sustenance to men who have poor means of controlling the fickle mother and are totally dependent upon her for survival.' Thus woman dominated symbolically in ancient India although this dominance was limited by Brahminic tradition by limiting her role in the social functioning and controlling her sexual liberty (or laxity depending on the point of view). This point can be seen clearly when one notices the matrifocal culture where femininity is linked with 'prakriti', or nature, and prakriti with leela, or activity. Similarly the concept of 'adya shakti', primal or original power, is entirely feminine in India. [2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the cruelest custom existed in India such as Sati, child sacrifice at Sagra Sangam, infanticide to ensure longevity of dams and buildings were all centered on some goddess. Some of most marginal groups in ancient India sought meaning as social being by being devotee of one 'Black' goddess or another, that is, speaking metaphorically, 'by identifying and being identified with an aggressive, treacherous, annihilating mother. In other words, as Ashis Nandy puts it, 'the ultimate authority in Indian male has always been feminine' [2].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies of child rearing in orthodox Indian families reveals that a woman (usually mother) has free emotional attachment to her [male] child. On one hand, child is dependent on her mother to an unusual degree and second and to others Indian child has distance relationship which is fragmentary and context based. Even the father acts as as outsider, who rarely come into the picture even to punish or reward the child. 'It is only with respect to his mother that Indian child is his whole self and recognizable as an individual.' The child sees his father more as a son of another woman than a husband of his mother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Indian mother, on the other hand, the son is major medium of self-expression. Her status in society is fixed by the status of her husband but her status in her house depends on the status of her sons. It is motherhood that traditional Indian family respects; her role as a wife is devalued and debased. Thus a woman self-respect in India family depends heavily on the status of her sons and for that matter she invests in them heavily. It is through his sons, she exercise her authority and defends her influence on her sons by all means possible. In traditional joint families, it is still a major source of tension between his newly wed-bride and his mother : a wife tries to claim her husband at the cost of a mothers' claim over her son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Associated with this in the son is a deep feeling of ambivalence towards her mother who is both controlling and discontinuous. The son tries to revolt yet he is helpless. He often sees her as a treacherous betrayer for not letting him out of her grip; controlling him by her always present nurture. One of our psychologists has noted that the India's fantasy life is to a great extent organized around the image of an angry, in-corporative, fickle mother, against whom his anger is directed and from whom through a process of projection, counter aggression is feared [5]. This ambivalence towards mother takes a form of ambivalence towards womanhood. In passing, it is worth noting that all major social reformists targeted the traditional concepts of woman and womanhood. On the other hand, the idea of mother was always invoked against the modern Western encroachments on Indian society ; and it is still invoked against cultural corruption. And so the woman as a symbol e.g. motherland, mother-tongue, are greatly praised in our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all may inculcates in a woman serious self-doubt. She starts undervaluing herself. She has to carry this added burden of 'greatness' which may not be at all compatible with her human nature. Majority of women, who never had access to 'modern or western thoughts' which advocate equality of gender, can be made to feel guilty whenever she tries to break the traditional norms of 'womanhood' by asserting her real self. This has changed in cities, although not to an extent to which many feminists wish. In cities, and even in towns, young women are coming out in open against such unwarranted demand of being devi or flag-bearers of their culture. This is a major source of irritation and anger of orthodox section of our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ambivalence towards woman in Western male is slightly different from that of Indian male. Western male fears the universal fear with Zilboorg speaks in his paper. In India society, leaving some strong martial cultures of Ganges plane, the man's fear is not that he will lapse in womanliness and thus loose is masculinity or potency. Indian males don't strive for potency as such. Unlike west, it is his ability to abstain from sex rather than hedonist display of sexual desires which is considered sign of sexual potency. The discomfort with and criticism of Nehru and Lady Mountbatten affair make one feels that great man are not suppose to get an erection in India. The masculinity fear here is that a man may fall foul of the cosmic feminine principle, that woman will betray, aggress, pollute, or at least fail to protect. The demand of motherly protection of man by his wife is best displayed in the story of Savitri where she saves her husband from death itself. Woman who failed to protect her husband from death were severely punished as widows, sometimes even burned as Sati. Now one can find an explanation why there is a common word 'randi' or 'rand'  used in Hindustani to describe both prostitutes and widows. There is a great deal of abhorrence for both : one pollutes their culture while other fails to protect. Although on our campuses this word heavily used by young boys and girls is more close to its English slang 'bitch'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian males are most likely to see a woman as women; a collective symbol and not an individual entity. There is an image of 'ideal or proper woman' in his mind. When he sees a woman different from this image, he is more prone to criticize the whole gender, and speak of its debasement. And in turn, more likely to demand a punishment, if he is caught in moral outrage. Even he is not into 'moral policing', he starts maintaining a safe psychological distance, and he tolerates other men cruelty towards women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have sympathy for Indian male in general for it is not entirely his fault for letting women take part of his mind and identity. Indian fathers do not play a significant part in emotional development of the child; and her mother -- whom the child also sees as a woman -- is given a free emotional ride over him. Deep emotional attachments (as well as partial identities) are known to extract heavy price from those who live with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No doubt that Indian woman have paid terribly and continue to pay for Indian male insensitivities, but they have also extracted a heavy toll from society by permanently residing in its psyche. Indian man has yet not learned to live with all aspect of womanhood which have always been much more different from the 'ideal image' of it in his head. And Indian women are confused if traditional roles assigned to them are good or bad; or incompatible with their modern inspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violence is a doubly edge sword. Those who tortured and killed people in wars also do violence to their families&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2013/feb/01/us-military-suicide-epidemic-veteran&quot;&gt; and themselves&lt;/a&gt;. A country which invades other countries also suffer from shooting spree at home. A fact which Gandhi understood very well. 'Modern psychology consolidates such belief', argues Nandy, that 'no marauder can hope to be a marauder without being a prey and no prey can not be a prey without being a marauder'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;END NOTES :
[1] Male aggression against women, An evolutionary perspective; Barbara Smuts.
[2] For an analysis of woman's identification with the aggressive male and her hostility towards womanhood see Karl Menninger, 'Love against Hate'. And 'Woman vs Womanliness in India', Ashis Nandy.
[3] Gregory also claims that male is a 'parasitic' fertilizer. I find it hard to believe. Human male also invest in his offspring. He is much more than a parasitic fertilizer. Human male is also choosy, perhaps more so in modern times than they were older times.
[4] See 'Sati – a Nineteenth century tale of women, violence and protest.', Ashis Nandy
[5] See Leela Dubey, 'On the construction of gender : Hindu girls in patrilineal India' where she explores 'the mechanisms through which women acquire the cultural ideas and values which-shape their images of themselves and inform the visions they have of the future.' She comments on 'the processes by which women are produced as gendered subjects in the patrilineal, patrivirilocal milieu of Indian society.' This article also examines the process of 'socialisation of Hindu girls through rituals and ceremonies, the use of language, and practices within and in relation to the family.'. EPW, April 30, 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]&lt;a href=&quot;http://india-seminar.com/semframe.html&quot;&gt; Indian male psyche, society and sexuality&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;( This article is most likely to incorporate changes and additional footnotes over time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;Related articles&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/open-page/rape-shame-and-the-curse-of-patriarchy/article4323558.ece&quot;&gt;Rape, shame and the curse of patriarchy&lt;/a&gt; (thehindu.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/columns/Vijay_Nagaswami/rapes-and-wrath/article4269072.ece&quot;&gt;Rapes and wrath&lt;/a&gt; (thehindu.com)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://r.zemanta.com/?u=http%3A//www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2013/jan/07/rape-culture-libby-brooks&amp;amp;a=136326088&amp;amp;rid=00000279-6b96-000F-0000-0000000000b6&amp;amp;e=f80899d0a950a7ed589239c0bb87e1cb&quot;&gt;We must all counter the mood music of rape culture&lt;/a&gt; (guardian.co.uk)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<published>2012-09-11 00:32:00 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/Gender/Indian Culture/Indian Society/2012/09/11/perception-of-women/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>In praise of : P. Sainath</title>
				<description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dilawarrajput.files.wordpress.com/2012/09/book1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dilawarrajput.files.wordpress.com/2012/09/book1.jpg?w=200&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&quot;IF this silly fellow keeps writing the things he does and saying the things he says, then he has no future at all. Certainly no one in power or positions of authority can ever forgive him,”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-- &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontlineonnet.com/fl2418/stories/20070921507010900.htm&quot;&gt;Khwaja Ahmad Abbas&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I try to do is look at the survival strategies of the poor, which is a much more interesting journalism. I try to focus not on the ‘events’ but on the ‘processes’ of poverty. In India we have what some writers have called a situation of ‘invisible hunger’. We do not have acute situations of famine (like in Somalia or the Sudan) but a more generalized distress. In the face of extreme exploitation, you see little kids who do not ‘look’ starving but they are very malnourished. In my reporting, I am engaged in a battle for minds and hearts. Why should I concede the readers of the press to the big press barons? I want to bring the Indian press back to its original mission. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; -- P. Sainath, in 1994&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;During my under-graduation in 2005, I read his article first time in Hindu newspaper. It was pleasingly surprising to notice someone in media knows villages and its life so well. Never before I had come across anything so authentically written on our lives in any newspaper. Journalists do write about villages and villagers but their writing is animated by wishful thinking. They rarely write about villagers as they see them. Even if they go to a village, they talk to some  'activist'  and next day his life is advertised as 'the ideal middle-class life' to their consumers. They are interested in eyeball-catching virtuous lifestyles and not in opinions of farmers and villagers on what is ailing them. He is altogether a very different breed of  journalist : he spends over 260 days a year in villages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of the journalists were busy lobbying for their consumers and advertisers, he showed no interest in becoming a 'stenographer to the powerful'. He was interested in bottom 10% of the society in an industry which cares about only top 10%. Since he compare and contrast the bottom 10% with the top 10%, it makes the top 10% uncomfortable. He holds the mirror in front of 'Beautiful People' and shows them their ugly spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graduated in history, he became an authority on rural economy and agriculture, and by extension, as Prof. Amartya Sen labeled him, one of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=9078987899127917834&quot;&gt;world's greatest experts on famine and hunger.&lt;/a&gt; He came under severe attack for not showing faith in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.india-seminar.com/2001/497/497%20p.%20sainath.htm&quot;&gt;religion of market&lt;/a&gt;. Nonetheless, He got many admirers. A supreme court judge wrote that his &quot;&lt;em&gt;name should be written in letters of gold in the history of India journalism&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. It must be! &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0459573/&quot;&gt;Documentaries were made&lt;/a&gt; on his journalism and his journalism is being &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Intp4IUphPo&quot;&gt;discussed in classrooms&lt;/a&gt;. Collection of his articles and news reports  are used as handbook by NGOs. In Scandinavia, the United Kingdom and Canada people found relevance in it for their own countries. In the United Kingdom it is being used by journalists to cover local issues of poverty and by more than 30 universities around the world, in the UK, Canada, and Australia. He has done a great service to his profession. Google scholar reports that his work is often cited in sociology and economics journals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are journalists for? Like intellectuals, they are the keeper of nation's conscience. Their primary job is to report. He belongs to a tribe where a journalist stands for some value. All radical journalists have stood for some value. And those who stand for some value not only report, they often provoke. They have the belief the it is OK to stretch the point somewhat if it serves a greater cause. Their work may not be immensely valuable for a sociologist but they preserve the truth for posterity. A journalist work is immensely valuable if a future historian can reconstruct the past from it. How many journalists today will pass the test of 'future historian'?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure how many professionals today like to be known by their work rather than the name of organization they work for. In those pre-color days, many believe that it was journalists who build a niche of their newspaper by their work; they wrote for public and in turn, they were hugely admired by public. They were inspiration to future journalists. Guardian's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2010/jan/25/cudlipp-lecture-alan-rusbridger&quot;&gt;editor-in-chief&lt;/a&gt; remembers why he loved some journalists because to him &lt;em&gt;&quot;they seemed to represent the best of journalistic virtues – courage, campaigning, toughness, compassion, humour, irreverence; a serious engagement with serious things; a sense of fairness; an eye for injustice; a passion for explaining; knowing how to achieve impact; a connection with readers ... but, more importantly, about why [journalism] mattered&quot;.&lt;/em&gt; If you are looking for any journalist who posses these qualities, ask for that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiatogether.org/opinions/psainath/&quot;&gt;incorruptible and feisty rural reporter&lt;/a&gt; named P. Sainath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sort of journalism which Sainath champions is on decline. For newspapers are increasingly getting more interested in eyeballs than what is connected with the eyeballs. They claim that they are forced to do it because this is what their readers want. This is odd for they rarely ask their readers what they want to read. Besides one of their heroes, Steve Jobs has proved that, 'consumers do not know what they want unless you show it to them'. Even if we believe for the sake of their argument that their readers are really interested in that sort of crap; this can not be expected from newspapers. For 'this is a kind of argument a drug paddler would make,'  says Sainath, 'Look! I am decent guy, these ass-holes on the street want this stuff. What can I do?'. Perhaps this is exactly the sort of thing which has happened. There is a little difference left between the business model of a drug paddler and a media house. The only difference between an newspaper and a drug paddler is that while the business model of a drug paddler is 'illegal' and low on public sympathy, newspapers can get away with the noise of 'self-regulation'. Media houses will do well to remember that this right of free speech -- indeed any right -- is not absolute. A society can not survive, let alone flourish, where its members care only for their rights and show no inclination for discharging their duties. Besides public sympathy is not an inexhaustible commodities. Ask Manmohan Singh. Someone will try to regularize it when they will find that public sympathy is no longer on the side of media. If there are some lessons to be learned from what is happening in U.K. after Leveson report, it is now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dilawar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2012-09-02 09:41:00 +0530</published>
				<link>http://dilawar.github.io/About a person/In Praise Of/Indian Media/2012/09/02/in-praise-of-p-sainath/</link>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
